<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A catalogue of the kings of Scotland Together with their seuerall armes, wiues, and issue.</title>
            <author>Milles, Tho. (Thomas), 1550?-1627?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11721</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22008</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120354</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855553</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855553</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21048</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11721)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21048)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 583:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A catalogue of the kings of Scotland Together with their seuerall armes, wiues, and issue.</title>
                  <author>Milles, Tho. (Thomas), 1550?-1627?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32, 31-32, 37-38 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By W. Jaggard],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.X.[1610]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Thomas Milles.</note>
                  <note>Intended to be issued with some copies of: Milles, Thomas.  The catalogue of honour (STC 17926).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  Kings and rulers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21048:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21048:1"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>decorative border</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>A CATALOGVE OF THE KINGS OF SCOTLAND. Together with their ſeuerall Armes, Wiues, and Jſſue.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> M.DC.X.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="Malcolm III" type="king">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:21048:2"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of King Malcolm III of Scotland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>MAlcolme,</hi> ſur-named <hi>Canmor,</hi> that is, <hi>Great-Head,</hi> the third of that name, King of <hi>Scots,</hi> was the eighty &amp; ſixt King after <hi>Ferguſius,</hi> that gouerned the kingdome of <hi>Scotland.</hi> This <hi>Malcolme</hi> was the ſonne of <hi>Duncan,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Crinanus</hi> Prince of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten vppon the Kinſwoman of <hi>Siward</hi> Earle of <hi>Northumberland.</hi> Vnto this <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colme, Edward the Confeſſor</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> gaue the kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to bee held of the Crowne of England, during the raigne of which <hi>Malcolme,</hi> King <hi>Edward</hi> dyed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edgar Aetheling,</hi> or <hi>Adeling</hi> (vnto whom in equiry the kingdome of his deceaſed Kinſman king <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſour appertained) at that time remaining in <hi>Hungary,</hi> with his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, his Siſter, and a great family, putting foorth to ſea, with intent to returne into his Natiue Countrey, being toſſed with contrary winds, at laſt landed vppon the coaſt of <hi>Scotland:</hi> where, being curteouſly entertained by this <hi>Malcolme,</hi> after much conference, and curteous offices (for at that time <hi>Malcolme</hi> ſpake the Engliſh tongue as his owne, which in thoſe ſeaſons was ſeldom vſed among the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nation, by reaſon that he had liued a baniſhed man, fourteene yeares of his youth in <hi>England</hi>) <hi>Margaret, Edgars</hi> ſiſter, for the excellent beauty and Noble carriage of her ſelfe in the Court of <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſo much pleaſed the fancy of <hi>Malcolme,</hi> that he deſired her for his wife, and married her. By whom he had ſixe ſonnes, and two daughters. <hi>William</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror, in the ſixt yeare of his raigne, ouerthrew this <hi>Malcolme</hi> in battaile, and of him as of his Leige-man, exacted the Oath of fealty and homage, which homage was performed (as ſaith <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Houedon</hi>) at <hi>Abernethy</hi> in Scotland. The like did <hi>William Rufus</hi> by the ſaide <hi>Malcolme</hi> and his two ſons, ſucceſsiuely raigning Kings, one after another, as it appeareth by the Chronicles of <hi>Florentius</hi> a Monke of <hi>Worceſter, William</hi> of <hi>Malmesbury, Roger Houedon, Henry</hi> of <hi>Hunting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and others. This <hi>Malcolme</hi> after he had raigned 37. yeares, and eight months, was ſlaine, with <hi>Edward</hi> his eldeſt ſonne, at the ſiedge of <hi>Almeric</hi> or <hi>Anwik</hi> a Caſtle in <hi>Northumberland, Anno. Dom,</hi> 1093. and lyeth buried at <hi>Tinemouth,</hi> hauing before builded the Churches of <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Dunfermeline</hi> in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He bore for his Armes, Or, a Lyon rampant Gules only, without any Treſſure at all: for wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it hath bin generally receiued, that the Treſſure hath beene vſed in the Armes of Scotland from the time of <hi>Achaius</hi> King of Scots, who firſt made league with the French, which giueth ſome colour to the matter, being garniſhed with Flour-de-luces. Yet I make a queſtion, vvho can proue any Armes, either with vs heer in England, or in Scotland, of that antiquity? Surely none, vntill of long time after, and much about the time of this <hi>Malcolme,</hi> if any at al then were. But out of all doubt, whenſoeuer they firſt began to bear Armes, they bore the Lyon, only with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any tract or treſſure, as is aboueſaid, which I find continued in that order, vntill the time of <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſecond King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as apeareth by his Seal, who in his ſhield bore this Lyon rampant ſimply, without any addition. And his ſonne <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, was the firſt that I finde, to vſe the treſſure floury, and that but a ſingle one neither, as you may ſee it cut in ſtone at Weſtminſter, in the time of the ſaid <hi>Alexanders</hi> raigne: which Treſſure, K. <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt vſed alſo but ſingle, in the ſeals which he made for the matters concerning his kingdom of Scotland. And I make no doubt, but that whenſoeuer this treſſure was firſt aſſumed, it did imply, and was a token of certain and ſure league made with the French, which afterward daily grew ſtronger and ſtronger, and to the intent that they would ſhew how willing they were to keepe it, of their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Treſſure, they made a double one.</p>
            <div type="wife">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21048:2"/>
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Margaret, wife of King Malcolm III of Scotland</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Argaret,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Edward the Out-law</hi> (ſon of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund Ironſide,</hi> King of England) &amp; ſiſter to <hi>Edgar Ethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> by whoſe death iſſuleſſe, ſhee was heire of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings and Monarchs: and Queene of <hi>Scotland,</hi> by mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of <hi>Malcolme</hi> the third, king of that Realme. She dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Caſtle of <hi>Edenborough,</hi> in the yeare 1093. vpon report of her husbands death, foure dayes after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe. For her ſanctity of life, ſhee was after her death, Cannonized a Saint, and remaineth regiſtred in the Kallender of Saints. Shee was no leſſe innobled by her mother <hi>Agatha,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth Emperor, Grand-childe vnto <hi>Lewis,</hi> and lineall deſcendant of <hi>Charles</hi> the great, then by her Father <hi>Edward,</hi> being the iſſue of ſo many holy and glorious Princes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="children">
               <list>
                  <head>Their Iſſue.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edward,</hi> who was ſlain with his Father at <hi>Alnwick,</hi> by the moſt valiant knight <hi>Morell,</hi> the 17. of the Calends of September, in the 37. yeare of the raigne of his Father.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edmund,</hi> who dyed a Child.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ethelred,</hi> dyed yong alſo</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edgar,</hi> who ſlew his Vncle <hi>Donevald,</hi> raigned in his ſtead, and helde <hi>Cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by the guift of <hi>william Rufus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Alexander,</hi> who after the deceaſe of his Brother, entered vpon the kingdome, and alſo held <hi>Cumberland</hi> by the graunt of <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dauid,</hi> who raigned after the death of his Brother <hi>Alexander.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Matild,</hi> or <hi>Mauld</hi> (ſur-named <hi>Bona</hi>) vpon whoſe Vertues, was made this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable Epigram, who was Queen of England, &amp; wife to k. <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt.
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Proſpera non laetam fecêre nec aſpera triſtem, Proſpera terror ei aſpera riſus erant:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Non decor effecit fragilem, non Sceptra Superbam, Sola potens humilis, Sola pudica decens.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mary,</hi> who was Counteſſe of <hi>Bullogne,</hi> married vnto <hi>Euſtace,</hi> Earle of <hi>Bullogn,</hi> vnto whom ſhe bare one daughter, <hi>Mauld,</hi> heire of the County of <hi>Bullogn,</hi> and married vnto <hi>Stephen,</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> vnto whom ſhe bare <hi>Euſtace,</hi> who dyed before his Father. She dyed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1115. the 27. of December.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="Duncan II to Alexander I" type="kings">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21048:3"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Kings Duncan II to Alexander I of Scotland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1096.</note>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Vncan,</hi> the baſe ſonne of <hi>Malcolme,</hi> and after him, <hi>Edgar</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> the lawfull children of <hi>Malcolme,</hi> ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely raigned ouer the Scots. This <hi>Duncan,</hi> forced <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevald,</hi> Brother vnto King <hi>Malcolme</hi> to fly his Country, and by the graunt and gift of <hi>william Rufus,</hi> King of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, raigned in his ſtead, after hee had performed his Oath of homage and fealty, made to the ſayde king <hi>william Rufus.</hi> And after the ſaid <hi>Duncan</hi> had raigned one yeare and an halfe, hee was ſlaine by <hi>Makpender,</hi> the <hi>Thane,</hi> and Earle of <hi>Mornes.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1007.</note>Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the ſame King <hi>william Rufus</hi> ſent <hi>Clito Edgar</hi> with an Army into <hi>Scotland,</hi> therein to ſeate his Brother in Law <hi>Edgar,</hi> the ſonne of King <hi>Malcolme,</hi> after the expulſion of his Vnckle <hi>Donevald,</hi> who vſurped vpon the kingdom: and he gaue vnto the ſaide <hi>Edgar</hi> the Kingdome, and receiued the accuſtomed homage and fealty. The ſaide <hi>Edgar</hi> deceaſed the ſixt of Ianuary, 1107. and vnto him ſucceeded <hi>Alexander</hi> his Brother, by the conſent of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the firſt, Anno. Dom. 1107. vnto whom he alſo gaue the like Oath of homage &amp; fealty. Seuenteene yeares raigned <hi>Alexander:</hi> but becauſe both himſelfe, as alſo his Brethren dyed iſſuleſſe, <hi>Dauid</hi> the youngeſt ſonne of King <hi>Malcolme,</hi> ſucceeded in the Kingdome, Anno. 1124. who being more worthy then both his Brethren raigned proſperouſly, 29. yeares, and two moneths.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="David I" type="king">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:21048:3"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of King David I of Scotland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1124</note>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Auid,</hi> commonly called Saint <hi>Dauid,</hi> the youngeſt ſon of King <hi>Malcolme</hi> the third, <hi>Edgar</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> his Brethren, beeing dead without iſſue, ſucceeded in the kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in the yeare of our Lord, 1124. Of proud perſons, hee (a valiaunt Prince) was the tamer and confounder; towards his good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, he was milde and mercifull; a Prince, Religious and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. He maruailouſly reformed the Scottiſh Nation, whoſe maners were very rude, &amp; alſo greedy of blood, out of their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage barbarouſnes ſo accuſtomed to bloodſhed, neither regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Age, nor Sex. He waged warre, and fought two mighty battailes with <hi>Stephen,</hi> King of England, aſſiſting the iuſt quarrell of his Neece the late Empreſſe. For vnto <hi>Mauld</hi> the Empreſſe, the Daughter and heire of King <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, and his Siſters el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Daughter, he had made his homage and fealty. For when King <hi>Stephen</hi> had ſent to demand homage of the ſaid King <hi>Dauid,</hi> for the Realme of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as for all other the Lands and Seigniories which he held of him within England: King <hi>Dauid</hi> made aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that both <hi>Stephen,</hi> he himſelfe, with all the Nobility of <hi>England,</hi> were all ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally bound by Oath, to the obedience of the Empreſſe his Neece, as the onely lineal and lawfull heyre to king <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, her Father, whereof hee for his part made that conſcience, as that during her life, hee would neuer acknowledge any other true inheritor to the Crown of England. Afterward notwithſtanding, he gaue his ſon <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> as hoſtage to k. <hi>Stephen,</hi> who in his Fathers behalfe did likewiſe ſwear homage vnto the ſaid K. <hi>Stephen.</hi> The Northern Prouinces of England (viz.) <hi>Northumberland</hi> &amp; <hi>Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland,</hi> he claimed in the name of <hi>Mauld</hi> the Empreſſe, which being gotten, hee long retained them as in his proper right, till King <hi>Henry,</hi> the ſon of the ſaid <hi>Mauld</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, diſgeſting with impatience, to be defrauded of ſo Noble a portion of his inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, regained the foreſaide Frontiers from King <hi>Malcolme,</hi> the Grand-childe of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> by his ſonne <hi>Henry.</hi> And thus after many troubles, King <hi>Dauid</hi> ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pt with his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in the yeare of our Lord, 1153. in the eighteenth yeare of King <hi>Stephen,</hi> the 24. day of May; declaring his Grand-childe, the eldeſt ſonne of his Sonne Earle <hi>Henry,</hi> as yet within age, his ſucceſſour in the kingdome. He lyeth buried at <hi>Dumfermeling.</hi> A Prince he was, of great Vertue and Honour, who after his honourable marriage, and his vndefiled bed, hauing one only ſon borne vnto him, he euer after remained a wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dower. He builded many Monaſteries; namely, <hi>Halyrude</hi>-house, <hi>Kelſo, Iedburgh, Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dranan, Cambuskeneth, Kinloſſe, Metroſſe, New-bottell, Dunfermelin, Holme</hi> in <hi>Cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and two Religious places at <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> in <hi>Northumberland.</hi> He erected four By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopprickes, (viz.) <hi>Roſſe, Brechin, Dumblane,</hi> and <hi>Dunkeld.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="wife">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:21048:4"/>
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Matild, wife of King David I of Scotland</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Atild,</hi> or <hi>Mauld,</hi> one of the daughters &amp; heires of <hi>VValtheof,</hi> earle of <hi>Northumberland</hi> and <hi>Huntington,</hi> and of <hi>Iudith</hi> his wife, the dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghter of <hi>Lambert</hi> Earle of <hi>Lens,</hi> Neece of <hi>william</hi> the Conqueror, was Wife to King <hi>Dauid,</hi> and Widdow of <hi>Simon Saint-Liz,</hi> Earle of <hi>Nort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umberland</hi> and <hi>Huntington.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="children">
               <list>
                  <head>Their Iſſue.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> Earle of <hi>huntington,</hi> the onely ſonne of King <hi>Dauid,</hi> married <hi>Adama,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>william</hi> the ſecond Earle of <hi>warren</hi> and <hi>Surrey,</hi> Siſter by the Mothers ſide, to <hi>william</hi> the younger Earle of <hi>warren</hi> and <hi>Surrey,</hi> to <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of Leiceſter, and <hi>walram</hi> Earle of <hi>Mellent</hi> in Normandy, and Worce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in <hi>England.</hi> Of whom, he got three ſonnes, and as many daughters. He dyed at <hi>Calcone,</hi> in the yeare of grace, 1151. his father being yet aliue, &amp; was there buried. His Lady <hi>Adama,</hi> founded a Monaſtery of Nuns at <hi>Hadington,</hi> and died in the yeare of our Lord, 1178.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Claricia,</hi> eldeſt daughter of King <hi>Dauid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hodierna,</hi> another daughter of King <hi>Dauid.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>The Children of Henry.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Malcolme,</hi> King of <hi>Scots,</hi> the fourth of that name, eldeſt Son of Earle <hi>Henry.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>VVilliam,</hi> King of <hi>Scots,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ather of <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſecond.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dauid,</hi> his third ſonne, Earle of <hi>huntington,</hi> that married <hi>Mauld,</hi> Siſter of <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulph</hi> earle of Cheſter, by whom he had diuers children.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Margaret,</hi> married to <hi>Conan,</hi> Earle of <hi>Brittaine,</hi> Anno. 1161. the ſeauenth of Henry the ſecond; after whoſe death, ſhe was againe married to Lord <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hun,</hi> earle of Hereford.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ada,</hi> married to <hi>Florence,</hi> earle of Holland.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mauld,</hi> who dyed in tender yeares vnmarried.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="Malcolm IV" type="king">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21048:4"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of King Malcolm IV of Scotland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1153.</note>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Alcolme,</hi> the fourth of that name (ſurnamed the <hi>Mayden,</hi> becauſe he would neuer marry, as heereafter is ſhewed) the Grand-childe of King <hi>Dauid,</hi> being thirteen yeares of age, ſucceeded in the kingdome of Scotland, in the yeare of Grace, 1153. <hi>Henry</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> ſon to the Empreſſe, inveſted this <hi>Malcolme</hi> with the Order of Knight-hood, and cauſed him to render vnto him the Countries of Northumberland and Cumberland, and in lieu thereof, reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him again to the earldome of Huntington, of ancient right appertaining vnto him; hauing firſt, performed his Oath of homage &amp; fealty for the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> at Cheſter, in the yeare of grace, 1160. The Countrey of <hi>Galloway</hi> in rebelling againſt him, he viſited in perſon with a mighty Armie, and ſubdued it. After he came vnto mans eſtate, the graue Counſellours of his kingdom perſwaded him to take a Wife; but he euer refuſed to hearken thereunto, conſtantly affirming, that he had vowed chaſtity, which he obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued all the daies of his life. He died at <hi>Iedworth,</hi> after he had raigned twelue yeares, and ſix months. But his body was buried at <hi>Dumfermling,</hi> a place ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing almoſt in the midſt of the kingdome, where for the moſt part the kings of <hi>Scotland</hi> haue beene accuſtomed to haue bin buried, euen to theſe our daies. After him, ſucceeded his Brother <hi>william,</hi> a man more fit for wordly affaires then his Brother, but for the Noble gouernment of the kingdome, hee could not be more happy then his Brother.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="William I" type="king">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:21048:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of King William I of Scotland</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Arma paterna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1165.</note>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Illiam,</hi> Earle of <hi>Huntington</hi> in England, Brother vnto <hi>Malcolme</hi> the fourth, ſucceeded in the kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp; was crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the yeare of Grace, 1165. This <hi>William,</hi> as alſo <hi>Dauid</hi> his Brother, with all the reſidue of the Earles and Barons of the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> became the Leidge-men of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the younger, the ſonne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, the day after his Coronation, and ſware vnto him fealty againſt all men, reſeruing their allegiances due vnto <hi>Henry</hi> the Father (as yet li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.) Howbeit, the ſame <hi>William</hi> hauing forgotten his duty, in hoſtile manner inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Countrey of Northumberland, with a puiſſant Army, in the twentieth yeare of Henry the ſecond, and vſed exceeding cruelty againſt the Inhabitants. Againſt whom, certaine Lords of Yorkeſhire, making out (viz.) <hi>Ranulph de Glanvill, Robert de Stuteuill, Bernard de Balliol, VVilliam de Veſey,</hi> and others, they tooke him priſoner at <hi>Alnwick</hi> or <hi>Anwick,</hi> and ſurrendered him vnto the foreſaide <hi>Henry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the yeare following, the fifteenth day before the Calends of May, hee was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to depart freely. And afterward, the ſayde <hi>VVilliam,</hi> by the conſent of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats, the Earles, Barons, and Nobles, and all others the chiefe perſons of Scotland, comming vnto Yorke, in the foreſaide yeare, the ſeauenteenth day before the Calends of September, he did acknowledge by his Letters Patents, vnto his Lord <hi>Henry,</hi> King of England, the ſonne of <hi>Maud</hi> the Empreſſe, that he, his heires and ſucceſſors, ſhould for euer be ſubiect vnto the Kings of England, as vnto their Leige-Lordes. After the deceaſe of King Henry, this <hi>william</hi> came againe to Canterbury, and did his homage vnto <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, the ſonne and heire of the ſaide <hi>Henry.</hi> And after his death alſo, the ſayde <hi>William</hi> did his homage, and ſwore his allegiance to <hi>Iohn,</hi> King of England, Brother and heire vnto the foreſaide <hi>Richard,</hi> on a heigh hil without the Citty of Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne, in the ſight of all the people, vpon the croſſe of <hi>Hubert</hi> Arch-Byſhop of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury. At laſt, falling grieuouſly ſicke, he departed this life at <hi>Striueling,</hi> the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Nones of December, in the yeare of Chriſt, 1214. in the ſeauenty and two yeare of his age, and the 49. of his raigne: or as others ſay, in the 52. and lyeth buryed at <hi>Abirbrothoke,</hi> a Monaſtery which he himſelfe had founded.</p>
            <div type="wives">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21048:5"/>
               <div n="first" type="wife">
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Ada, first wife of King William I of Scotland</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <head>The firſt wife.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ADa,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Robert de Auenell,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Scot. Chronicon.</hi> was the firſt wife of king <hi>willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> whoſe name and progeny to other Chroniclers are not very wel knowne; perhaps, for that he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried her, as yet being but a priuate perſon, and are therefore ſilenced or omitted of Hiſtoriographers. But his daughter <hi>Adama,</hi> begotten vpon her, he married vnto <hi>Patric</hi> of <hi>Dunbar,</hi> Earle of March.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="second" type="wife">
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Ermengardis, second wife of King William I of Scotland</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <head>The ſecond wife.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ERmengardis,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Richard</hi> Viſcount <hi>Beaumont,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalin,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Beaumont,</hi> &amp; of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> the baſe daughter of <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt and Kinſwoman to <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, was the ſecond wife of King <hi>William.</hi> She was married vnto him at Woodſtocke, in the Nones of September, in the yeare of our Lord, 1186. by <hi>Baldwin,</hi> Arch-Byſhop of Canterbury, in the 33. yeare of the raigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond. Shee founded the Monaſtery of <hi>Bulmurinagh,</hi> &amp; died the 3. Ides of Febr. 1233. in the 47. yeare after hir eſpouſals, &amp; lies buried in <hi>Bulmurinagh</hi> being of hir own foundation, as aforeſaid.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="children">
               <list>
                  <head>Children by his ſecond wife.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Alexander,</hi> King of Scots, borne vpon the feaſt day of Saint <hi>Bartholomew</hi> at <hi>Hadington,</hi> 1198.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henry,</hi> ſlaine by his Vnckle <hi>Malcolme.</hi> He was Father vnto <hi>Patric Galightly,</hi> one of the twelue Competitors for the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iſabel,</hi> maried to <hi>Roger Bigot</hi> Ea. of <hi>Norffolke,</hi> and Earl Marſhall of England: and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to <hi>Robert</hi> Lord <hi>Roos, de Hamelak:</hi> from whom, diſcended <hi>William</hi> Lorde <hi>Roos,</hi> another Competitor of the kingdome of Scotland.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Margaret,</hi> married to <hi>Hubert de Burgh,</hi> Earle of <hi>Kent,</hi> 1221. who dyed without iſſue by her.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mariorie,</hi> perhaps baſe, married to Lord <hi>Euſtace</hi> of <hi>Veſey,</hi> vnto whom ſhe brought the Barony of <hi>Sprouſton</hi> for her Dowry.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aufric,</hi> married to <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Say</hi> in <hi>Ireland:</hi> from whom deſcended <hi>Roger de Amunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile</hi> or <hi>Mundeuile,</hi> a Competitor alſo of the ſayde kingdome.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="Alexander II" type="king">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:21048:6"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of King Alexander II of Scotland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1214.</note>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lexander</hi> the ſecond, after the deceaſe of <hi>William</hi> his Father, was crowned King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> at <hi>Scone,</hi> on the feaſt day of S. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas,</hi> with great honour, beeing but ſixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene yeares old and an halfe, when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to raigne. A Prince, ſurely worthy of gouernment, &amp; a man who towards the poore was bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, cherriſhed the good, abhorred the euill, and accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to doo right vnto all men with Iuſtice and equity. Hee obſerued the peace moſt faithfull, with King <hi>Iohn,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> his ſonne: vnto the which <hi>Iohn,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to his ſonne <hi>Henry,</hi> hee did his homage for the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Scotland.</hi> And pacifying the rebellious Iſlanders, he departed the way of all fleſh, at <hi>Kerueray,</hi> in the weſt Iſles, in the yeare of our Lord, 1249. the ſecond day of Iune, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter almoſt thirty and fiue yeares of his happie and fortunate raigne, and lieth buried in the Monaſtery of <hi>Melros,</hi> in the 51. yeare of his age, and the 35. of his raigne.</p>
            <div type="wives">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:21048:6"/>
               <div n="first" type="wife">
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Joane, first wife of King Alexander II of Scotland</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <head>The firſt wife.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IOane,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Iohn</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> and ſiſter to King <hi>Henrie</hi> the third, was Queene of Scotland, and the firſt wife of King <hi>Alexander,</hi> being eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto him, in the yeare of Chriſt, 1221. at Yorke, who comming out of Scotland deſired to viſite <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and in her returne towards London, died, the fourth of the Nones of March, leauing behinde her no iſſue, Anno. 1238. She lieth buryed betweene the Armes of <hi>Henry,</hi> K. of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and <hi>Richard</hi> Earle of <hi>Cornwal,</hi> her Brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, in the Church of <hi>Tharent.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="second" type="wife">
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Mary, second wife of King Alexander II of Scotland</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſecond wife.</hi> 
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MAry,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Ingelram</hi> of <hi>Guines,</hi> L. of <hi>Coucy</hi> in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond wife to K. <hi>Aexander.</hi> She was maried to him at <hi>Roxburg</hi> in Scot. in the year 1239. on <hi>Whitſonday.</hi> She di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, 1282. beyond the ſeas.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="children">
               <list>
                  <head>His Iſſue by the ſecond wife.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> borne at <hi>Roxburg,</hi> the one and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty day of Auguſt, 1240.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Margaret</hi> a Daughter, married to one <hi>Alan le Huſee,</hi> vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe brought forth <hi>Ermengard</hi> a Daughter alſo, maried to one whoſe ſur-name was <hi>de Seu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les.</hi> From whom <hi>Nicholas de Seules,</hi> one of the Competitors for the kingdom of Scotland diſcended.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="Alexander III" type="king">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:21048:7"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of King Alexander III of Scotland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1249.</note>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lexander</hi> the third, the ſonne of <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſecond, after his deceaſe, was crowned King of Scotland. And becauſe this <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> at the death of his father was but nine yeare old, a great feare poſſeſſed the Gouernours of the child, leaſt vpon contempt of his Nonage, vſurpations on euery hand ſhould bee inforced vpon the Kingdome. Whereupon, in all haſt, Meſſengers in the Kings name were diſpatched vnto <hi>Henry</hi> the third, King of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, both to continue the ancient league and amity, as alſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt his daughter for their King in mariage, wherunto, K. <hi>Henry</hi> granted in all points, &amp; ſo <hi>Alexander</hi> tooke <hi>Margaret,</hi> the Daughter of the ſaid King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> for his wife, and afterward did his homage to the ſaide <hi>Henry</hi> Father in in Lawe, and to his ſonne <hi>Edward,</hi> for the kingdome of Scotland. At laſt, in the yeare of our Lorde, 1285. The 19. day of March, the ſaide <hi>Alexander</hi> falling from his horſe, vpon the ſandes on the North ſide of <hi>Kyngorne,</hi> and breaking his neck, dyed, in the 37. yeare of his raign, and lyeth buried at <hi>Dunfermeling,</hi> hauing formerly builded the croſſe Church of <hi>Peibles.</hi> After whoſe death, the kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> for the ſpace of ſixe yeares, and nine mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, had no Gouernour, which produced many lamentable greeuances (as ſhall heer-after appeare.) He left one onely daughter and heire vnto the kingdome (named <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret</hi>) and ſhe was married vnto <hi>Eric,</hi> King of <hi>Norway;</hi> who bare alſo another <hi>Margaret,</hi> (commonly called the <hi>Maiden</hi> of <hi>Norway,</hi> who preſently after her Mother, alſo deceaſed iſſueleſſe. Whereupon, Controuerſie aroſe, as concerning the ſucceſsion. For the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome lay vacant by the tearme of ſixe yeares, and nine months, as aforeſaide, the ſtate being promiſcuouſly gouerned by ſixe Vice-royes or Gouernours. The Gouernors for the South-ſide of <hi>Forth,</hi> were <hi>Robert</hi> Arch-Byſhop of <hi>Glaſquo, Iohn Cumin,</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> great Steward of <hi>Scotland:</hi> for the North-ſide of <hi>Forth,</hi> were appointed <hi>Macduff,</hi> Earle of <hi>Fife, Iohn Cumin</hi> Earle of <hi>Buckquhane,</hi> and <hi>William Frazer</hi> Arch-Byſhop of S. <hi>Andrewes,</hi> who being al worn out, at laſt, by the iudgement of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt King of England, <hi>Iohn Balliol</hi> tooke vpon him the ſupreame authority ouer that kingdome.</p>
            <div type="wives">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21048:7"/>
               <div n="first" type="wife">
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Margaret, first wife of King Alexander III of Scotland</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <head>The firſt wife.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MArgaret,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and Siſter vnto <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, was wife vnto <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, King of <hi>Scotland.</hi> Shee vvas married vnto him at <hi>York,</hi> vpon the feaſt day of the Natiuity of our Lo. 1251. and dyed 1274. at <hi>Cupſum,</hi> the fourth of the calends of March, and lieth buried hard by King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> commonly called Saint <hi>Dauid.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="second" type="wife">
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Joletta, second wife of King Alexander III of Scotland</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <head>The ſecond wife.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IOletta,</hi> Daughter of the Earle of <hi>Dreux,</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> ſecond vvife vnto <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, King of Scottes, whom he married, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing good hope to leaue yſſue by her to ſucceede him. She vvas ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried vnto him in the yeare of our Lord, 1286. by whom hee left no ſucceſſor.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="third" type="wife">
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Margaret, third wife of King Alexander III of Scotland</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <head>The third wife.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MArgaret,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Guy de Dampier,</hi> Earle of <hi>Flanders,</hi> was third wife vnto this <hi>Alexander</hi> the thirde, by whom ſhe had no iſſue. Shee was afterwarde againe married to the Earle of <hi>Guelders.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="children">
               <list>
                  <head>Children by his first wife.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Alexander,</hi> who dyed an vntimely death in the life time of his father, vvas borne at <hi>Iedworth,</hi> the 12. calends of Ianuary, 1264.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dauid,</hi> vvho alſo dyed in the life time of his Father.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Margaret,</hi> married to <hi>Eric</hi> of <hi>Norway,</hi> ſonne of <hi>Magnus,</hi> King of <hi>Norway.</hi> Of vvhom vvas borne another <hi>Margaret,</hi> the onely future heire of the kingdome of Scotland. Who being promiſed in marriage to Prince <hi>Edward,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, King of <hi>England,</hi> comming out of <hi>Norway</hi> to be married, in her iourny about the <hi>Orchades,</hi> being very young, dyed. Whereupon, great contentions ariſing, concerning the ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the kingdome, <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, King of <hi>England,</hi> in the 18. yeare of his raigne, ſummoned the Scottiſh Nobility to a Parlament at <hi>Norham,</hi> there declaring vnto them his right of Soueraignty, Paramount ouer the kingdome of <hi>Scotland.</hi> Which being acknovvledged by the ſaid <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nobility, and ſeiſin and poſſeſſion of the Land and the Caſtles of the kingdom, being deliuered to him by the Competitors, he cauſed diuers In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments &amp; Duplicats thereof to be ſealed by them, vvhich to moſt of the chiefeſt Monaſteries of his realme, he ſent to be preſerued for poſterity. He then receiued in the claimes of the ſeueral Competitors: Of vvhich, the greateſt right, and only diſcent of title, ſeemed to bee betweene <hi>Robert de Brus,</hi> and <hi>Iohn de Balioll,</hi> both being diſcended from <hi>Dauid</hi> Earle of <hi>Anguſe</hi> and <hi>Huntington,</hi> Brother to <hi>Malcolme</hi> and <hi>William,</hi> and Vnckle to <hi>Alexander</hi> the laſt King, to whom he was next heire, &amp; he ſuruiued the iſſue of his Nephew. <hi>Robert de Brus,</hi> the eldeſt ſon of <hi>Iſabell,</hi> the daughter of the foreſaid <hi>Dauid,</hi> claimed a preſedency of right, as being by a degree nearer in blood then <hi>Balioll,</hi> to the laſt King, which was conſonant to the law of Nations, the fitteſt rule to ſquare out the intereſt of Kings. But either wearied as ſeemeth with the trouble of Competitor, or willing to ſhew a rare example of moderation in his election of a priuate life, hee reſigned vp his claime and interreſt of that kingdome to his ſonne. The Original deed ſtill remaining with <hi>Sir Robert Cotton,</hi> the heire of <hi>Bernard de Brus,</hi> his ſecond Brother, and is in theſe words:
<q>
                        <hi>OMnibꝰ Christi fidelibꝰ hoc praeſens ſcriptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> viſuris vel audituris Robertꝰ de Brus Dominus de valle Anandia ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in domino. Nouerit vniuerſitas veſtra nos conceſsiſſe &amp; omnino remiſiſſe kariſsimo filio noſtro domino Roberto de Brus Comiti Karrik. &amp; haeredibus ſuis, totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ius &amp; clamium quod habuimus vel habere potuimus ad petendum reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Scotiae, Ita quod nos nihil Iuris aut clamij ad praedictum regnum, nomine noſtro petendum de caetero vendicare aut exigere poſſumus damus inſuper &amp; ſpontanea voluntate concedimus praedicto filio noſtro &amp; heredibus ſuis plenam &amp; liberam potestatem dictum regnum petendi, &amp; ius quod ſibi competit in hac parte nomine ſuo proſequends prove voluntate ſui melius nouerit conuenire &amp; omnia faciendi que per nos ante tenorem confectionis praeſentium poterunt expediri. In cuius rei teſtimonium praeſenti ſcripto ſigillum noſtrum appoſuimus et in Maius teſtimonium ſigillum No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21048:8"/>
viri Domini Gilberti de Clare Comitis glouerniae &amp; Hertford preſentibus apponi procurauimus. Datum apud</hi> Berwic, <hi>die veneris in Crastino ſancti, Leonardi, Anno. gratiae,</hi> 1292.</q>
                     <p>But in concluſion, <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt finding <hi>Balliol</hi> an eaſier inſtrument, apter to lean to his deſire either of reducing that kingdom to his immediate obedience, or at leaſt for retaining it within the reach of his ſoueraignty, preferred him for King, being the ſonne of <hi>Deruergilla,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Margaret,</hi> the firſt begotten daughter of <hi>Dauid,</hi> Earle of <hi>Huntington,</hi> great Vnckle vnto this <hi>Alexander</hi> the third.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="John" type="king">
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of King John of Scotland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">He was crowned the laſt day of Nouember, at Scone, vpon Saint Stephens day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</note>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ohn Balliol,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iohn Balliol,</hi> and of <hi>Deruerguld</hi> his wife, the Daughter of <hi>Margaret,</hi> the eldeſt Daughter of <hi>Dauid</hi> Earl of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tington,</hi> great Vnckle vnto <hi>Alexander</hi> the third (who dyed without iſſue) by the ſuffrage of <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, King of <hi>England,</hi> was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced vnto the Royall Throne of the kingdome of Scotland, and did the accuſtomed homage, and ſwore allegiance vnto the ſayde King <hi>Edward,</hi> at the Towne of <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> vpon <hi>Tine,</hi> in the yeare of our redemption, 1292. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>M. ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; ter C. ſed ab illis octo c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>herce, Hoc anno Domini tradidit d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ma Iohanni.</hi>
               </note> For three yeares, and ſomewhat aboue, this <hi>Balliol</hi> gouerned the ſtate of <hi>Scotland:</hi> But, for that he prooued ſlouthfull and negligent, the Scots depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him, as an vnprofitable member, in the yeare of our Lorde, 1292. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Chron. lib.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.</note> From whence, he fled into <hi>France,</hi> and there dyed. Whereupon, <hi>Edward</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> for ten yeares ſpace, miſerably afflicted the Scottiſh Nation, and by force entred the kingdome as farre as the Riuer <hi>Forna,</hi> where is the paſſage to <hi>Ros.</hi> Heere by the way it is to be noted, <note n="*" place="margin">Some ſay it was this mans father.</note> that this <hi>Iohn Balliol</hi> founded that Colledge in Oxford, 1263. which to this day beareth his owne name there: whoſe Grand father (by the Father ſide) <hi>Alexander Balliol,</hi> in like manner (as others his predeceſſors) were owners of <hi>Bernard</hi> Caſtle in the Byſhoppricke of <hi>Durham:</hi> which ſayde Caſtle it is reported, that one <hi>Bernard Balliol,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after the Conqueſt of England by the Normans, erected, and named it after his owne name.<note place="margin">Betweene the raigne of this Iohn, and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Brus, Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Walleys, with ſome others, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed themſelues againſt Edward, k of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. The which Walleys being afterwarde taken. Edw. the 1. did hang at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, &amp; cauſed his quarters to be fix<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed vpon poles in many places in Scotland. Anno. 1305.</note>
            </p>
            <div type="wife">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:21048:8"/>
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Isabell, wife of King John of Scotland</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Sabell, the Daughter of Iohn, Earle Warren and Surrey, was wife vnto this Iohn Balliol, King of Scotland.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="children">
               <list>
                  <head>Their Iſſue.</head>
                  <item>Edward de Balliol, who after the death of Robert Brus, entred his fathers inheritance, and tooke vpon him the ſupreame authority of the kingdome of Scotland.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="Robert I" type="king">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:21048:9"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of King Robert I of Scotland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1306.</note>
               <hi>RObert le Brus,</hi> Earle of <hi>Carict,</hi> (the ſonne of <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of <hi>Carict,</hi> great Nephew of <hi>Iſabell,</hi> the ſecond Daughter of <hi>Dauid</hi> Earle of <hi>Huntington,</hi> great Vnckle vnto <hi>Alexander</hi> the third) hauing now put <hi>Balliol</hi> to flight, aſſumed the kingdome of Scotland, from which he held himſelfe ſo long vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly debarred. And ſo vpon the feaſt day of the Annunciation of our bleſſed Lady, he was crowned King in the Monaſtery of <hi>Scone,</hi> in the year of Grace, 1306. But <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, king of <hi>England,</hi> deſirous to repreſſe his actions, for his own aduantage, leuied a puiſſant army againſt him, vnder the direction &amp; Lieutenancy of <hi>Aumary de Valence,</hi> Earle of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> at that time Deputy &amp; gouernor of the kingdom of <hi>Scotland;</hi> who at <hi>Methwen</hi> encou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tred the ſayd K. <hi>Robert:</hi> wherein the ſaid <hi>Robert</hi> was ouerthrowne and put to flight, the 19. of Iune, 1306. But reinforcing his ſtrength, he oftentimes renewed the war with <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, ſecond, and third, Kings of <hi>England,</hi> and was the mirrour of Chiualry in thoſe dayes. This valiant King after he had raigned 24. yeares, being ſtroken with a Leproſie, dyed at <hi>Cardros,</hi> 1328. the 7. of Iune, the 2. of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, and lieth buried in the Monaſtery at <hi>Dunfermeling.</hi> King <hi>Robert</hi> being dead, <hi>Thomas Ranulph</hi> Earle of <hi>Murrey,</hi> was made Gouernour of the kingdome; but hee was poyſoned at <hi>Muſſelburg,</hi> the 13. of Auguſt, 1332. It is reported, that <hi>Robert</hi> vpon his death-bed, willed three things in his Teſtament. Firſt, that the Kings of Scotland ſhould neuer alienate the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Iſlands nor beſtow them on great perſonages. Secondly, that the <hi>Scottes</hi> ſhould neuer giue a long nor determinate day vnto the Engliſh to fight on. Thirdly, he willed his heart to be deliuered vnto ſome woorthy knight, that had vowed himſelfe to the warres in the Holy-Land, to carry it into the field with him, whenſoeuer he ſhold fight againſt the Infidels: which accordingly he bequeathed vnto that Noblema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Iames Douglas,</hi> for that he had heertofore made a Vow, that in proper perſon he would vndertake to fight againſt the Infidels aforeſaide.</p>
            <div type="wives">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21048:9"/>
               <div n="first" type="wife">
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Isabell, first wife of King Robert I of Scotland</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <head>The firſt wife.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ISabell,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Doneuald,</hi> Earle of <hi>Mar,</hi> the ſiſter of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> Earle of <hi>Mar,</hi> was wife of <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of <hi>Carict,</hi> who dyed before he had fully gotten the kingdome. <hi>Robert</hi> her husband beeing the ſecond time ouerthrowne at <hi>Dalry.</hi> And as ſhee fled into <hi>Ros,</hi> was taken, and brought into England, vnto King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, and in England remained vntill the battell of <hi>Bannock,</hi> commonly called the battell of <hi>Bannocks B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rne,</hi> fought in the time of King Edward the 2.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="second" type="wife">
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Elizabeth, second wife of King Robert II of Scotland</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <head>The ſecond wife.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ELizabeth,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer de Burgo,</hi> Earl of <hi>Vlſter</hi> in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> was the ſecond wife of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Brus,</hi> King of Scotland, who dyed the 26. of October, Anno Dom. 1327.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="children">
               <list>
                  <head>His Iſſue by his firſt wife.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Marioria,</hi> married to that Nobleman <hi>VValter Steward,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iames Steward,</hi> who dyed the ſeauenteenth of the Calends of Auguſt, 1309. great Seneſchall of <hi>Scotland,</hi> vnto whom ſhe brought foorth <hi>Robert Steward,</hi> who ſucceeded <hi>Dauid le Brus,</hi> in the Kingdome of Scotland. It was couenanted at <hi>Aire,</hi> 1315. by the Nobles of the kingdome, that if King <hi>Robert</hi> deceaſed without heire male, that then his Brother <hi>Edward Brus,</hi> ſhould be King. And if the ſayde <hi>Edward</hi> alſo dyed without male, that then, this <hi>Marioria,</hi> and ſo others of the kings Daughters, ſhould ſucceede, in caſe they married to the good liking of the King and the Realme.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>His Iſſue by the ſecond wife.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dauid,</hi> who ſucceeded his Father in the kingdome.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Margaret,</hi> married to the Earle of <hi>Sutherland,</hi> who dyed in bringing forth, of <hi>Iohn</hi> her ſonne. Which <hi>Iohn,</hi> dyed a pledge in England for his father <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid.</hi> And according to the intaile, had ſucceeded, as deſcended from the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſonne, if he had liued.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Maud,</hi> married to <hi>Thomas Iſaac,</hi> by whom he had two daughters, <hi>Ioane</hi> &amp; <hi>Katherine,</hi> that dyed at <hi>Striueling,</hi> by whom hee had this <hi>Maud,</hi> it appeareth not.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="Edward" type="king">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:21048:10"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of King Edward of Scotland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Dward Balliol,</hi> the onely ſonne of <hi>Iohn Balliol,</hi> King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> came into <hi>Scotland</hi> after the deceaſe of <hi>Robert Brus;</hi> affirming, that the kingdome appertained vnto him. And at <hi>Duplin</hi> obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a great victory againſt the Guardians of <hi>Dauid Brus,</hi> and of the kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> by the aſsiſtance of <hi>Edward</hi> the thirde, King of <hi>England,</hi> by the ſword he made good way to his foreſaid claime to the kingdome of Scotland, and accordingly tooke vpon him the regall Dignity, in the Monaſtery of <hi>Scone,</hi> the foure and twentith day of September, Anno. Dom. 1332. With whom tooke part, <hi>Dauid</hi> Earle of <hi>Atholl, Henry de Beaumont,</hi> Earle of <hi>Bucquhane, Gilbert de Vmfrauille,</hi> Earl of <hi>Angus, Raph</hi> Baron of <hi>Stafford, Richard Talbot,</hi> and many others the Nobles of England, who had Title vnto Lands in the ſame kingdome, in right of their wiues. The ſecond yeare after, this Edward, King of Scots, did his homage vnto Edward the third, at <hi>New-Caſtle</hi> vpon <hi>Tyne,</hi> for the whole kingdome of Scotland, and the adiacent Iſles, vpon the Feaſt day of <hi>Saint Geruais</hi> and <hi>Prothaſius,</hi> the fourteenth Calends of Iuly, in the yeare of grace, 1333. Vpon occaſion of which homage, the Commons of Scotland roſe againſt both the kings in diuers parts of the kingdome. Whereupon, <hi>Balliol</hi> was inforced for a time to make his abode in England. In the <hi>Interim</hi> whereof, <hi>Dauid</hi> the ſon of <hi>Robert Brus,</hi> as yet a Child, and in the cuſtody of <hi>Thomas Randolph,</hi> Earl of <hi>Murrey</hi> Protector, is crowned King: who afterwards growing vnto mans eſtate, proued a Prince of no leſſe ſpirit then his Father, but not ſo fortunate. For <hi>Edward Balliol</hi> (<hi>Dauid</hi> as yet being yong, and <hi>Thomas Randolph</hi> deceaſed) inuaded the kingdome, and put <hi>Dauid</hi> to flight; who together with his Wife, (the Siſter of <hi>Edward</hi> the third) was inforced to flye into France, where he lay obſcurely, eight yeares and more. But at laſt, <hi>Dauid</hi> preparing for his returne, hee was receyued with the generall applauſe of the people, and <hi>Balliol</hi> reiected, neceſſity inforcing him to flye into England, vnto King <hi>Edward.</hi> Where weighing with himſelfe his manifolde e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections; at laſt, freely releaſed vnto Edward the third, King of England, his intire right vnto the kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> for the ſum of 2000. pound yeares for his maintainance, as appeareth by good record, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Breuia directa Baronibus,</hi> 38. <hi>Edward,</hi> 3. <hi>in Scaccario.</hi>
               </note> (viz.) <hi>Termino Michaelis, An.</hi> 38. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Rex conceſsit Edwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do de Baliolo nuper Regi Scotiae ex cuſtuma portuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Kingeſton &amp; Sancti Botolphi,</hi> 2000. li. <hi>ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Annuis ad ſuſtentatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conuencionem factu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inter dictum Eduardum Regem An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae, &amp; praedictum Edwardum de Baliole de conceſsione corone &amp; iuris regni ſui Scotiae.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="David II" type="king">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:21048:10"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of King David II of Scotland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1329.</note>
               <hi>DAuid Brus,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Robert Brus,</hi> after the eiection of <hi>Balliol,</hi> in the yeare of our Lord 1329. was cald out of France (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee had now liued to mans eſtate,) to take on him the gouerment and rule of the Realm of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as King thereof, and vppon the 24. day of Nouember, in the yeare of Chriſt 1331. in the eight yeare of his age, and the thrid of his raign, in the Parliament at <hi>Scone,</hi> hee receiued the order of Kinght-hood at the hands of that Noble-gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Tho. Randolph</hi> Earl of <hi>Murry.</hi> The day following hee was Crowned, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed with great honor (before whom, neuer was there any King of <hi>Scotland</hi> Crowned or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed.) Vpon the ſameday, was alſo crowned and annointed <hi>Iohan</hi> his Q. Againſt this <hi>Dauid, Edward Balioll</hi> waging war, beſiedged <hi>Barwicke,</hi> to whoſe aide alſo came that victorious Prince, King <hi>Edward</hi> the third. In the yeare of our Lord 1333. the 19. of Iuly, in the battaile at <hi>Halidon-Hill,</hi> where were ſlayne 7. Earles, of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons and Knights 900. Eſquires 400. and 3000. common Souldiers, &amp; <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> was taken by the ſaid King <hi>Edward</hi> the third the day after, being the 20. of Iuly. In this <hi>Dauids</hi> time alſo <hi>Edward</hi> the 3. beſiedged <hi>Calis,</hi> which was then in the poſſeſſion of <hi>Phillip</hi> of <hi>Valois</hi> the French King. Whereupnn this <hi>Phillip</hi> ſent his ambaſſadors into <hi>Scotland</hi> vnto King <hi>Dauid,</hi> that according to their league he ſhould enter <hi>England,</hi> ſo to diuert his enemy <hi>Edward,</hi> from the ſaid ſiedge of <hi>Calis.</hi> Who condiſcending vnto the <hi>French</hi> King, aduentured to inuade England, with a right puiſſant army of Scotſh-men, preſuming, that <hi>Edward</hi> had left behind him none but church-men, &amp; husband-men; and that the flower of the ſoldierie of England, had been ouer ſea with the King their Soueraign. Whereupon, he Marched as far as <hi>Durham,</hi> where he was fought withal, and ouerthrowen by the inhabitants of <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> &amp; ſome few others: He himſelfe, with <hi>william Douglas,</hi> and many others of the Nobles taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, by <hi>Iohn Coupland</hi> an Eſquier of the North and commited to ſafe cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, vpon the vigil of Saint <hi>Luke</hi> the Euangeliſt, in the yeare of Grace 1346. Thoſe that fought the ſaid victorious battaile, were <hi>william Le-Zouch</hi> Arch-Byſhop of Yorke with the Clergy of his Dioces, <hi>Gilbert de Vmfrauill</hi> Earle of <hi>Anegos, Henry Percy, Ralph Neuill, william D'eyncourt,</hi> and <hi>Henry Le-Scrope,</hi> with a very ſmall Army of Engliſh-men, ſuch as they could aſſemble in ſuch a penurious ſeaſon. The tenth yeare after, being ranſomed, hee ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a very modeſt Prince to the end of his life, which was at <hi>Edenburg</hi> in the 47. yeare of his age, and the 39. of his raigne; in the yeare of our Lord 1370. leauing no yſſue behind him to ſucceed him. He lieth buried in the Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Saint <hi>Croſſe,</hi> before the great Alter there.</p>
            <div type="wives">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:21048:11"/>
               <div n="first" type="wife">
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Johan, first wife of King David II of Scotland</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <head>The firſt wife.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iohan</hi> (ſurnamed of the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer) the daughter of king <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, King of <hi>England,</hi> and Siſter vnto King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, was the firſt wife of <hi>Dauid</hi> King of <hi>Scots.</hi> who iorny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into <hi>England</hi> to ſee her Brother, there dyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iſſue; and lieth buried at <hi>London,</hi> in the Church of the <hi>Friers Minorits.</hi> Hee Married her at <hi>Barwicke</hi> the 17. of Iuly 1238.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="second" type="wife">
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Margaret, second wife of King David II of Scotland</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <head>The ſecond wife.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MArgaret Logi,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Iohn Logi</hi> Knight, a <hi>Virgin</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celling all other of that time for beauty, was the ſecond Wife of King <hi>Dauid,</hi> whom (as hee himſelfe boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted) he married rather for her form, then in deſire of yſſue. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, when hee perceiued that ſhee had accompliſhed the age of foure and twentie yeares, and grew hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of Iſſue, he forſooke her. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon, ſhee appealed vnto the court of Rome, and after the expence of much Treaſure, (to no purpoſe,) ſhe dyed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="Robert II" type="king">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:21048:11"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of King Robert II of Scotland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1371.</note>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Obert Stewart,</hi> ſur-named the <hi>Hunter,</hi> the Nephewe of <hi>Dauid Brus,</hi> by his Siſter, he was ſon of <hi>walter Stewart,</hi> begotten vppon the body of <hi>Margery,</hi> the ſiſter of King <hi>Dauid,</hi> by the generall agreement of the whole Scottiſh Nation, is nominated king in ſtead of his deceaſed vncle, vpon the feaſt day of the Anunciation of our bleſſed Lady, in the year of our Lord, 1371. Againſt whom, in the very beginning, <hi>william Douglas</hi> oppoſed himſelfe, affirming, that the right of that kingdome accrued vnto him by the aliance with the <hi>Balliols</hi> and <hi>Comyns.</hi> But perceiuing that <hi>George</hi> of <hi>Dunbarre,</hi> Earle of March, and his Brother the Earle of <hi>Murrey,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Erskine,</hi> (who had three of the ſtrongeſt fortreſſes of the kingdome in their cuſtodies, (viz:) the Caſtle of <hi>Maydens, Striueling,</hi> and <hi>Dunbreton</hi>) did ſtrongly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe againſt him, whereupon he renounced his pretenſion. And at laſt, the daughter of King <hi>Robert,</hi> borne in lawfull wedlocke, was giuen in marriage to <hi>Iames,</hi> ſon and heire of the ſaide <hi>william Douglas.</hi> This <hi>Robert</hi> amongeſt the Scots, was the ſecond King of that name, and the firſt of the <hi>Stewarts:</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which Sur-name, and vnder nine Kings of the name, for the ſpace of two hundred yeares and more, euen vnto this day, haue the Scottes bin happily gouerned, and the famous Jſle of Great <hi>Brittaine</hi> in our dayes, into one Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment vnited, by our dread Soueraigne Lord King <hi>Iames,</hi> that now is. Vnto any of whom, this <hi>Robert</hi> was nothing inferiour in happineſſe, as the man, whom during the whole time of his raigne, neuer felt the affliction of any aduerſe fortune. He dyed with age, and not with ſickneſſe, the 13. of the Calends of May, in the yeare of our Lord, 1390. and in the 19. yeare of his raigne, in his Caſtle of <hi>Deidon,</hi> being full of dayes, (viz.) in the 74. yeare of his age, and lyeth buried in the Monaſtery of <hi>Scone.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="wives">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21048:12"/>
               <div n="first" type="wife">
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Eufemia, first wife of King Robert II of Scotland</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <head>The firſt wife.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>EVfemia,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Hugh</hi> Earle of <hi>Ros,</hi> was the firſt lawfull wife of this <hi>Robert</hi> King of <hi>Scotland.</hi> who not long after hir husband <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> was crowned in ſolemne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, 1372. She died in the third year of his raigne, and in the year of our Lord, 1387.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="second" type="wife">
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Elizabeth, second wife of King Robert II of Scotland</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <head>The ſecond wife.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ELizabeth,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Adam Moore,</hi> knight, was the ſecond wife vnto this King ROBERT, By whom, he hadde three Sonnes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="children">
               <list>
                  <head>His Iſſue by his firſt wife.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>VValter Stewart,</hi> Earle of <hi>Atholl,</hi> beheaded for plotting Treaſon againſt <hi>Iames</hi> the firſt.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dauid Stewart,</hi> Earle of <hi>Stratherne.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Eufemia,</hi> married vnto <hi>Iames,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>william Dowglas.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>His Iſſue by the ſecond wife.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn,</hi> afterward named <hi>Robert,</hi> and ſucceeded his Father in the kingdome.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert Stewart,</hi> Duke of <hi>Albany,</hi> Gouernor of Scotland, and Earle of <hi>Fife</hi> in right of his wife, and was Father of <hi>Mordac,</hi> Duke of <hi>Albany,</hi> and Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Scotland.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Alexander Stewart,</hi> Earl of <hi>Bucquhane,</hi> father of <hi>Duncan</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>A daughter, married to <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Dunbarre,</hi> the Brother of <hi>George</hi> Earle of March.</item>
                  <item>A ſecond daughter, married vnto <hi>Iohn Lyon,</hi> Lord <hi>Glammys,</hi> but of what name, or by what woman theſe two were, appeareth not in record.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="Robert III" type="king">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:21048:12"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of King Robert III of Scotland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Obert Steward</hi> the third of that name, King of <hi>Scottes,</hi> Earle of <hi>Carict,</hi> whoſe name was firſt <hi>Iohn,</hi> ſucceeded his deceaſed Parent <hi>Robert</hi> the ſecond, in the yeare of our Lord, 1390. He chaunged his name, as I conceiue, for that he deemed the name of <hi>Iohn,</hi> ominous &amp; vnfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate; as firſt, being hatefull in the <hi>Balliols;</hi> and ſecondly, vpon animaduerſion, that a king of <hi>France</hi> of that name was in battell taken priſoner by the Engliſh. This third <hi>Robert</hi> in a manner, waged continuall warfare with England, but alwaies with vncertaine and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate ſucceſſe. Who after he had raigned ſixteene yeares, and ſeen <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> one of his Sonnes made away by the ſubtilty of <hi>Robert</hi> Duke of <hi>Albany,</hi> &amp; Earle of <hi>Fife,</hi> his Vnckle; and his other Son <hi>Iames</hi> in declining, by the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his ſaide Vnkle, to be captiuated by the Engliſh, wherein hee ſhewed himſelfe a Prince more vertuous then polliticke: for with the Engliſh, his childe might haue beene in better ſecuritie then amongſt his owne people; for mony or mariage might haue wrought his deliuerance, as the euent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Their owne Annales record, that this <hi>Robert</hi> was a good man, but no good King. Hee dyed at <hi>Bucquhane,</hi> the fourth of the Calends of Aprill, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Palme-ſunday, in the yeare of our Lord, 1406. and lyeth buried at <hi>Paſlet.</hi> From this time, for the tearme of thirteene yeares, was the kingdom gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Lieutenants (viz.) <hi>Robert,</hi> and after him, by <hi>Mordac</hi> the ſon of <hi>Robert;</hi> which time being almoſt expired, <hi>Iames</hi> the Son of this <hi>Robert,</hi> beeing freely deliuered out of <hi>England,</hi> returned, and tooke vpon him the Royal Dignity.</p>
            <div type="wife">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21048:13"/>
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Anabel, wife of King Robert III of Scotland</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nabel,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Iohn Drummond de Stubhall,</hi> Knight, was wife vnto this <hi>Robert</hi> the third. A Lady for her admirable beauty, deer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued of her husband. She died at <hi>Scone,</hi> 1401. and lieth buried at <hi>Dunfermeling.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="children">
               <list>
                  <head>Their Iſſue</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dauid,</hi> their firſt borne Duke of <hi>Rothſay,</hi> who dyed of hunger.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iames,</hi> who ſucceeded his father in the kingdom, and was the firſt of that name.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Egidia,</hi> married to Earle <hi>Dowglas,</hi> who had iſſue, one onlie daughter, married to <hi>Henry Sinclare,</hi> earl of the <hi>Orchades,</hi> from whom is deſcended <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> Earle of the <hi>Orchades.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Daughter maried vnto the Earle of <hi>Angus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A Daughter married vnto the Earle of <hi>Dalketh.</hi> By what woman theſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ee da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters were, is not man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>feſt by war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of any of our records.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="James I" type="king">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:21048:13"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of King James I of Scotland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ames Stewart,</hi> the firſt of that name amongſt the Scots, the ſon of <hi>Robert</hi> the third, after his long and tedious abode in <hi>England,</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on certain conditions and couenants was freely deliuered, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning into Scotland, was re-aduanced to the regall throne in the yeare of grace, 1422. and in the next yeare following, hee made his homage for the kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> at <hi>windſor,</hi> vnto <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt King of <hi>England</hi> his ſuperiour Lord, <hi>Anno. Dom.</hi> 1423. This <hi>Iames</hi> was a Prince of an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent wit, very couragious; an excellent Wraſtler, ſwift of foot, a good Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, and inferior to no man in eloquence of ſpeech; all which, he had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitely learned in England, during the time of his long captiuity. He was no leſſe commendable for his Poeſie in the Scottiſh tongue, whoſe Booke and Verſes euen to this day, amongſt the Scots, carry the prize and beſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation. By the Treachery of his Vnckle the Earle of <hi>Atholl</hi> (who euer carried an aſpiring mind vnto the kingdome) he was wounded to death with thirty deadly ſtabbes, in the Towne of <hi>Perth,</hi> the 21. of February, in the yeare of grace, 1447. and was buried at the <hi>Carthuſians,</hi> in the one and thirtith year of his raigne, and the four and fortith of his age: for whom, he himſelfe had built an houſe in the Suburbs of the ſame Towne. The parricides, the Earle of <hi>Atholl,</hi> and <hi>Robert Graham</hi> were puniſhed moſt cruelly, but moſt worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>Graham</hi> was reported to haue alledged for his excuſe, that becauſe the K. had proſcribed and baniſhed him, that therefore hee was not his ſubiect. So friuolous an excuſe had the man of ſinne, for euer and euer infamous, taken for his preſumptuous offence. Whereuppon, the Scots haue this Rithmicall Prouerb in their owne language amongſt them:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Robert Gramen, he ſlew our King,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>God giue him ſchamen.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <div type="wife">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:21048:14"/>
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Jone, wife of King James I of Scotland</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>One</hi> (the daughter of <hi>Iohn Beaufort,</hi> Earle of <hi>Somerſet</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> whom the ſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> begot vppon the bodie of <hi>Margaret</hi> his wife, Dutcheſſe of <hi>Clarence,</hi> Siſter &amp; one of the co-heyres of <hi>Edmund Holland,</hi> Earle of <hi>Kent</hi>) was wife vnto this <hi>Iames</hi> the firſt King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> marryed vnto him at <hi>London,</hi> in the year of our Lord, 1423. who after the death of King <hi>Iames,</hi> tooke to her ſecond huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, <hi>Iames Steward,</hi> a young Gentleman, by whom ſhee had three Sonnes; the firſt, called <hi>Iohn,</hi> was Earle of <hi>Atholl;</hi> the ſecond, called <hi>Iames,</hi> was Earle of March, and the third ſonne was thought to be Byſhop of <hi>Murrey.</hi> She di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the fourth of the Nones of March. Anno Dom.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="children">
               <list>
                  <head>Their Iſſue.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Alexander,</hi> who dyed an Jnfant.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iames,</hi> the ſecond king of Scots after his father. Twinnes.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Marg.</hi> eldeſt daughter maried to <hi>Lewis</hi> the xij. k. of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ioan,</hi> Dutcheſſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Dutcheſſe of <hi>Brittaine.</hi> All yſſueleſſe.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>This King had three other Daughters, one mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to the Earle of <hi>Camphire</hi> in <hi>Zeland.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Another married to the Lord of <hi>Dalketh.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Annother to the Earle of <hi>Huntley.</hi> All dyed yſſueleſſe. By what Women theſe three Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were, is not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="James II" type="king">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:21048:14"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of King James II of Scotland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ames,</hi> the ſecond ſon of <hi>Iames</hi> the firſt, after the death of his father, was made King of Scotland, in the yeare of our Lord, 1447. Hee was called <hi>Iames</hi> with the fiery face, becauſe he had a verie red mole on the one ſide of his face. This King, when hee came to mans eſtate, grew very ſtrong, &amp; tooke to wife, the daughter of the Duke of <hi>Gheldres.</hi> He arreſted the Earle of <hi>Douglas, William</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> his Brothers, with <hi>Nicholine Hemming,</hi> Lord of <hi>Comirnald,</hi> at the Tower of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and cauſed them all to be beheaded vpon the Mount with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſaide Caſtle. From this time, after the death of <hi>Dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas,</hi> he raigned Royally, and made Lawes according to his owne will; and afterward being at the ſiedge of <hi>Roxbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough</hi> Caſtle (which the Engliſh had long held) where hee was very curious about the framing of warlicke Engins to aſſault the Caſtle, was there ſlaine by a great ſhot from the Caſtle, &amp; the Earle of <hi>Angus</hi> ſtanding by, was ſorely woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the third day of Auguſt, in the year of our Lord, 1460. in the 29. yeare of his age, and the 24. of his raigne. He was royally buried in the Monaſtery of S. Croſſe at <hi>Edinburgh.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="wife">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:21048:15"/>
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Margaret, wife of King James II of Scotland</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Argaret,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Arnoldus</hi> of <hi>Egmont,</hi> Duke of <hi>Gheldres</hi> (was wife vnto the ſaide <hi>Iames</hi> the ſecond) deſcended anciently from the race of the Dukes of <hi>Brunſwicke.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="children">
               <list>
                  <head>Their Iſſue.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iames,</hi> the third King of <hi>Scots,</hi> next following.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Alexander Steward,</hi> Duke of <hi>Albany.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Steward,</hi> Earle of <hi>Marre,</hi> who dyed yſſueleſſe.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Anna,</hi> firſt married to <hi>Alexander,</hi> Lord of <hi>Boyd,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Lord <hi>Hamilton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Margaret,</hi> married to the Lord <hi>Creichton.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="James III" type="king">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:21048:15"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of King James III of Scotland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ames</hi> the third, being a child of ſeuen yeares of age, after the death of <hi>Iames</hi> the ſecond his father, was Crowned King of Scots, at <hi>Calcon.</hi> in the yeare of our Lorde, 1460. and when hee was twentie yeare old, he tooke to wife <hi>Margaret,</hi> the dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghter of the King of <hi>Norway,</hi> and was marryed at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> which brought him in dower the pretended right of the Kings of Norway, to the <hi>Orchad</hi> Iſlands, and the reſt of the Iſlands there adiacent. In the beginning of his raigne, he ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led al things in quiet order, but in his latter time, by aduerſe fortune, the moſt part of his Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity conſpired againſt him. He dyed at <hi>Sterling,</hi> in the yeare of our redemption, 1488. the xi. of Iune, in the 28. yeare of his raigne.</p>
            <div type="wife">
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Margaret, wife of King James III of Scotland</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MArgaret</hi> (Daughter of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> and <hi>Norway</hi>) was wife to the ſaide <hi>Iames</hi> the third, King of Scots.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="children">
               <list>
                  <head>Their Iſſue.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iames</hi> the fourth King of Scots, after the death of his Father.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Steward,</hi> Earle of <hi>Marre,</hi> who dyed without iſſue.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Alexander Steward,</hi> Byſhop of Saint <hi>Andrewes,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Albany,</hi> died with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iſſue.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="James IV" type="king">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:21048:16"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of King James IV of Scotland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ames</hi> the fourth, after the death of his father <hi>Iames</hi> the third, got vnto himſelfe great power amongſt the <hi>Scots,</hi> which for ſome yeares he very directly adminiſtred Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice by the ſame, and brought the kingdom vnto much quietneſſe by his good gouernment. Inſomuch, that the great thefts, robberies, ſlaughters, and ſuch like vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies which had beene commonly vſed in Scotland, (about the borders eſpecially) were euery where almoſt vtterly left off. But <hi>Lewes</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King vſed great and many perſwaſions vnto King <hi>Iames,</hi> that he ſhould not deſiſt in theſe bloudy enterpriſes, but rather increaſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the rather, thereby to offend <hi>Henry</hi> King of England, whoſe Siſter the ſayde <hi>Iames</hi> had married, and with whom hee had great league. At length through many hard perſwaſions and faire promiſes from the French King, hee leuyed a great power, and at a time vnexpected, inuaded England, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though (preſently after it was knowne) he was admoniſhed by King <hi>Henry,</hi> that although he were not aſhamed of his deed, at leaſt hee ſhould feare the iudgement of Almighty God, who is wont to be reuenged on the perturbers of peace, and the breakers of leagues. For that warre being taken in hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all faith, and league ſworne, had like euent, for by the Engliſh they were ouerthrowne, and King <hi>Iames</hi> himſelfe was ſlaine in that battel, &amp; with him, one Arch-Byſhop, two Byſhops, foure Abbots; Noblemen &amp; Knights 34. beſides 8000. common ſouldiers, and almoſt all the reſt taken Captiues, alſo all their Enſignes; and 22. great peeces of Ordinance. This battaile was fought at <hi>Floddon-Hill,</hi> neere <hi>Branxton,</hi> a Towne in <hi>Northumberland,</hi> the 9. day of September, Anno. Dom. 1513.</p>
            <div type="wife">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:21048:16"/>
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Margaret, wife of King James IV of Scotland</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Agaret,</hi> the daughter of king <hi>Henry</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth, and Siſter to the moſt Noble King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, was wife vnto this K. <hi>Iames</hi> the fourth, who after the death of the ſaide King her husbande, was againe married to <hi>Archibald Dowglas,</hi> earl of <hi>Angus,</hi> hauing by him a daughter, called <hi>Margaret,</hi> borne at <hi>Hare-bottel</hi> Caſtle in <hi>England,</hi> Anno. 1516. who was wife vnto <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew Stewart,</hi> Earle of <hi>Lenox,</hi> Mother of <hi>Henry,</hi> which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried <hi>Mary,</hi> Queene of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and who were Father &amp; Mother to our moſt dread Soueraigne Lord <hi>Iames,</hi> King of Great <hi>Brittaine, France, and Jreland,</hi> defender of the Faith, &amp;c. whom God long preſerue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="children">
               <list>
                  <head>Their Iſſue.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Arthur,</hi> firſt ſonne, dyed the 14. of <hi>Iuly,</hi> 1510 in the life time of his Father.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iames,</hi> the fifth King of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Alexander,</hi> born 1514. after his fathers death, D. of <hi>Rothſay.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="James V" type="king">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:21048:17"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of King James V of Scotland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ames</hi> the fift, his Father being ſlaine in England, was k. of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in the yeare of our Lord, 1513. being but a childe of a yeare olde, when his father dyed, and was crowned, Anno Dom. 1515. at <hi>Scone,</hi> at which place, the Kings of <hi>Scotland</hi> haue beene vſually inaugurated. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this King there was diuers conflicts, as wel by land as by Sea, betweene both Nations. <hi>Iohn</hi> Duke of <hi>Alba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> Nephew to the deceaſed King, by the graue Counſell of the Realm, was ſent for home out of France, to protect the young King, and to gouerne his land, and when he had aſſumed the gouernment, preſently after, he with the French, began to make warre againſt the Engliſh, and all thoſe great Lordes whom he thought to haue forſaken the King in his warre, hee put to death: for which cauſe, much diſtruſting his owne ſafety, he returned into France, and King <hi>Iames</hi> now comming vnto mans eſtate, he tooke to wife <hi>Magdalen,</hi> eldeſt daughter to <hi>Francis</hi> the French king, who liued not aboue one yeare with him. After whoſe death, hee married <hi>Mary,</hi> daughter to the Duke of <hi>Guiſe;</hi> by whom hee left one onely daughter liuing. King <hi>Iames</hi> dyed with griefe of mind, in the Caſtle of <hi>Falkeland,</hi> the xiiij. of December, Anno. 1542. after whoſe death, <hi>Iames</hi> Earle of <hi>Arran</hi> Lord of <hi>Hamilton</hi> his Kinſman, was conſtituted Gouernour to the young Queene, and alſo her Tutor.</p>
            <div type="wives">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:21048:17"/>
               <div n="first" type="wife">
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Magdalen, first wife of King James V of Scotland</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <head>The firſt wife.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MAgdalen,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Francis</hi> K. of France, the firſt wife to <hi>Iames</hi> King of <hi>Scots,</hi> who dyed without iſſue.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="second" type="wife">
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Mary, second wife of King James V of Scotland</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </head>
                  <head>The ſecond wife.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MAry</hi> of <hi>Lorayn,</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Claudius</hi> Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and Siſter vnto <hi>Duke Francis,</hi> and Widdowe of <hi>Longuevill,</hi> was the ſecond wife to <hi>James</hi> the fift, which <hi>Mary</hi> died, Anno. 1560.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="children">
               <list>
                  <head>His Iſſue by his ſecond wife.</head>
                  <item>IAMES</item>
                  <item>ARTHVR Both died Infants.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mary,</hi> Queene of Scots, borne the ſeauenth day of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> on the vigil of the Conception of our bleſſed La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the Virgin, Anno. 1542.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="Mary I" type="king">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:21048:18"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Queen Mary I of Scotland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ary,</hi> onely daughter of <hi>Iames</hi> the fift, King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> being an infant at the time of her Fathers death, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared heire to the kingdome of <hi>Scotland, Anno.</hi> 1542. her Gouernour in her tender yeares, was <hi>Iames</hi> Earle of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran,</hi> Lorde of <hi>Hamilton</hi> her Kinſman, who was alſo her Tutor. He for the ſaide Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> waged war with the Engliſh, denying to giue her in marriage to <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, King of England, notwithſtanding it was ſo agreed vppon by the chiefe Peeres of both kingdomes, which cauſed the battell at <hi>Muſſelborough</hi> field, where the Engliſh were Victors. The Duke of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> Vnckle &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector to the King, and <hi>Iohn</hi> Earle of Warwicke, after made Duke of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland,</hi> being Generals; at firſt, the battell grewe doubtfull on which ſide it would fall, but at length it happily fell on the Engliſh ſide, in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of Auguſt, 1547. Queene <hi>Mary</hi> now comming to her prime yeares, was firſt married to <hi>Francis</hi> Dolphin of <hi>France,</hi> the fourth of December, 1566. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whoſe death, ſhe was ſecondly married to <hi>Henry Steward,</hi> Lorde <hi>Darnley,</hi> eldeſt Sonne to <hi>Mathew,</hi> Earle of <hi>Lenox,</hi> by <hi>Margaret Dowglas:</hi> who begot of the ſaide <hi>Mary,</hi> a Childe of an excellent wit, and great hope, 1566. &amp; was chriſtened. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Queene of <hi>England,</hi> of famous memory; <hi>Charles,</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Philebert</hi> Duke of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> being God-fathers and God-mother: and named <hi>Charles-Iames,</hi> who now by true right of deſcent, is Ki. of Great <hi>Brittaine, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, &amp;c. whome. God long preſerue.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="James VI" type="king">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:21048:18"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of King James VI of Scotland</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>AMES, King of Great Brittaine, France, and Ireland, Defender of the Faith, was ſonne of Mary, Queene of Scots, and of Henrie Stewart her ſecond husband, was borne at Edinburgh, in the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of Maydens, the 19. of Iune, 1566. firſt crowned and annointed King of Scotland, at Sterling, the 29. day of Iuly. Anno. 1567. in the ſecond year of his age: and in the year of our Lord, 1603. hee was moſt happily crowned and annointed King of England, France, and Ireland.</p>
            <div type="wife">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:21048:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>royal blazon and crown of Anne, wife of King James VI of Scotland</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nna,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Fredericke</hi> the ſecond, King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke</hi> and <hi>Norway,</hi> and Siſter of <hi>Chriſtiern</hi> the fourth now King, was married to King <hi>Iames,</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt, after the vſuall manner of marrying ſuch perſons, the Kings themſelues not beeing there. This marriage was ſolemnized at <hi>Gonemburgh,</hi> a Citty in <hi>Denmark,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there efpouſed to <hi>George Keith,</hi> Earl Marſhall, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of the North parts of Scotland, and of <hi>Marre,</hi> then Embaſſador for the ſaide King. This Queene <hi>Anne</hi> was borne at <hi>Scanderburg,</hi> the twelfe day of December, 1574.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="children">
               <list>
                  <head>Their Iſſue.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henry,</hi> Prince of <hi>VVales,</hi> Duke of <hi>Cornwall, Rothſay,</hi> and Earle of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> was borne on Tueſday, the 19. of February, 1593.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iames,</hi> dyed young.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Charles,</hi> Duke of Yorke and <hi>Albany,</hi> Earle of <hi>Ros,</hi> and Lorde of <hi>Ardmanoch.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> borne the 19. of Auguſt, 1596.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Margaret,</hi> borne the 24. of December, 1598. dyed in Scotland.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mary.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sophia.</hi> Both dyed young, and lieth buryed at Weſtminſter.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:21048:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
